<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
<channel><title>Geeklog RSS Feed from geeksta.net</title>
    <link>/geeklog/rss.xml</link>
    <description></description>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 May 2024 23:14:45 </lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Logya</generator>
    <docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs>
    <item>
        <title><![CDATA[The Centenarian Decathlon: A Practical Guide to Thriving into Your 90s and Beyond]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[https://geeksta.net/geeklog/the-centenarian-decathlon/]]></link>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>Future-proof your independence with the Centenarian Decathlon. Build resilience, energy, and confidence in your 50s through smart, practical training.</p>]]></description>
        <guid><![CDATA[https://geeksta.net/geeklog/the-centenarian-decathlon/]]></guid>
        <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:43:41 </pubDate>
        <content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <h2 id="what-is-the-centenarian-decathlon">What is the Centenarian Decathlon?</h2>
<p>The <strong>Centenarian Decathlon</strong>, introduced by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Attia">Dr. Peter Attia</a>, is not a sporting event but a <strong>longevity framework</strong>. It’s a way to prepare your body for the movements and activities that matter most in everyday life so you can remain strong, independent, and active into your 90s and beyond.</p>
<p>The idea is simple: picture yourself at age 100 and ask, <em>What do I still want to be able to do?</em> These become your personal <em>events</em>. By identifying them now and training deliberately, you build the strength, endurance, balance, and mobility to sustain those abilities later in life.</p>
<h2 id="common-events-in-the-centenarian-decathlon">Common Events in the Centenarian Decathlon</h2>
<p>Each person’s list is personal, but certain functional activities tend to matter most. These examples are broken down by gender for someone in their 50s planning ahead.</p>
<h3 id="males">Males</h3>
<ol>
<li>Lift and place a 30–40 lb suitcase in an overhead bin.</li>
<li>Carry two grocery bags (20–30 lbs each).</li>
<li>Get off the floor unassisted.</li>
<li>Climb 2–3 flights of stairs without stopping.</li>
<li>Pick up a child or grandchild (25–40 lbs).</li>
<li>Walk briskly for 1–2 miles.</li>
<li>Push open heavy doors or move objects around the house.</li>
<li>Perform yardwork or shovel snow safely.</li>
<li>Balance on one leg for 30 seconds.</li>
<li>Hike 2–3 hours on uneven terrain with a light pack.</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="females">Females</h3>
<ol>
<li>Lift and carry 15–25 lbs (laundry basket, suitcase, or child).</li>
<li>Carry grocery bags (10–15 lbs each).</li>
<li>Get up from the floor unassisted.</li>
<li>Climb stairs while holding a small load.</li>
<li>Lift and place an object overhead (like a bag of flour).</li>
<li>Walk briskly for 1–2 miles.</li>
<li>Balance on one leg for 30 seconds.</li>
<li>Pick up a grandchild or pet (20–30 lbs).</li>
<li>Do household tasks requiring stamina.</li>
<li>Enjoy recreational hikes or walks on uneven ground.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="training-in-your-50s-building-the-foundation">Training in Your 50s: Building the Foundation</h2>
<p>Your 50s are a <strong>critical decade</strong> for building the reserve capacity that will carry you through the natural decline of later years. Think of it as making a deposit into your future health bank.</p>
<h3 id="males-50s">Males (50s)</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Strength</strong>: Deadlifts, squats, pull-ups, farmer’s carries, overhead press.</li>
<li><strong>Mobility</strong>: Turkish get-ups, floor-to-stand drills, deep stretches.</li>
<li><strong>Endurance</strong>: Zone 2 cardio (brisk walking, cycling, rowing) 3–5× weekly.</li>
<li><strong>Balance</strong>: Single-leg stance, heel-to-toe walking, Tai Chi.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="females-50s">Females (50s)</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Strength</strong>: Squats, dumbbell presses, kettlebell deadlifts, rows.</li>
<li><strong>Mobility</strong>: Sit-to-stand practice, Turkish get-ups, yoga.</li>
<li><strong>Endurance</strong>: Brisk walking, swimming, or elliptical, 3–5× weekly.</li>
<li><strong>Balance</strong>: Cushion stands, dance, Pilates, or Tai Chi.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="weekly-training-blueprints">Weekly Training Blueprints</h2>
<h3 id="comprehensive-plan-56-days">Comprehensive Plan (5–6 Days)</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Strength training</strong>: Alternate upper/lower body sessions.</li>
<li><strong>Cardio (Zone 2)</strong>: 45–60 minutes, 2–3× per week.</li>
<li><strong>Mobility &amp; balance</strong>: 10–15 minutes daily.</li>
<li><strong>Weekend activity</strong>: Outdoor hike, cycling, or sports that involve uneven terrain and real-world movement.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="minimalist-plan-3-days">Minimalist Plan (3 Days)</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Day 1 – Strength Foundation</strong>: Deadlifts, presses, rows, carries.</li>
<li><strong>Day 2 – Endurance + Balance</strong>: Zone 2 cardio + single-leg balance work.</li>
<li><strong>Day 3 – Functional Strength</strong>: Turkish get-ups, step-ups, squat-to-press.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="progression-roadmap-50s-70s">Progression Roadmap: 50s → 70s</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>50s: Build capacity.</strong> Focus on heavier lifts, endurance, and mobility.</li>
<li><strong>60s: Preserve and refine.</strong> Maintain strength, increase recovery time, and prioritize durability.</li>
<li><strong>70s: Maintain independence.</strong> Focus on lighter loads, fall prevention, and mobility for daily living.</li>
</ul>
<p>The principle is clear: <em>build a surplus of strength and endurance now so you have plenty to draw from later.</em></p>
<h2 id="self-assessment-scorecard">Self-Assessment: Scorecard</h2>
<p>A simple <strong>fitness report card</strong> can help you track readiness. Re-test every 6 months to monitor progress.</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Test / Benchmark</th>
<th>Males (50s)</th>
<th>Females (50s)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><strong>Deadlift (5 reps)</strong></td>
<td>1.25× bodyweight</td>
<td>1.0× bodyweight</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Farmer’s Carry</strong></td>
<td>50% bodyweight each hand, 40m</td>
<td>25% bodyweight each hand, 30m</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Sit-to-Stand (30 sec)</strong></td>
<td>15 reps</td>
<td>12 reps</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>1-Mile Walk</strong></td>
<td>≤ 15 minutes</td>
<td>≤ 16 minutes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Single-Leg Balance (eyes closed)</strong></td>
<td>10 seconds</td>
<td>5 seconds</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="why-it-matters">Why It Matters</h2>
<p>The Centenarian Decathlon isn’t about aesthetics or chasing athletic records — it’s about living better today while preparing for tomorrow. By training strength, mobility, endurance, and balance, you unlock more energy, fewer aches, deeper sleep, and the freedom to fully enjoy everyday life right now.</p>
<hr>
<p>Thank you for reading!</p>
<p>This article was written by Ramiro Gómez using open source software and the assistance of AI tools. While I strive to ensure accurate information, please verify any details independently before taking action. For more articles, visit the <a href="https://geeksta.net/geeklog/">Geeklog on geeksta.net</a>.</p>        ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title><![CDATA[The Pros and Cons of Cron Jobs]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[https://geeksta.net/geeklog/the-pros-and-cons-of-cron-jobs/]]></link>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>Discover the pros and cons of cron jobs, their benefits, limitations, and best practices for effective task automation in Unix-based systems.</p>]]></description>
        <guid><![CDATA[https://geeksta.net/geeklog/the-pros-and-cons-of-cron-jobs/]]></guid>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 23:38:33 </pubDate>
        <content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <p>Cron jobs have been a cornerstone of task automation in Unix-based systems for decades. They're versatile, lightweight, and relatively simple on the surface. However, as with any tool, their effectiveness depends on how they're used, the context in which they're applied, and the mindset of those implementing them.</p>
<p>In this article, I'll first outline the technical advantages and disadvantages of cron jobs for those who are new to the concept or looking to refresh their understanding. Then, I'll move into a more human-centered perspective, acknowledging why some swear by cron jobs and why others, like me, feel they might be a double-edged sword.</p>
<h2 id="what-is-a-cron-job">What Is a Cron Job?</h2>
<p>Before we dive in, let's clarify what a cron job is. A cron job refers to a scheduled task configured to run automatically at predetermined intervals. These intervals are defined using cron's unique syntax, which allows for a high degree of customization.</p>
<p>Common uses of cron jobs include automating backups, rotating logs, refreshing data, or running health-check scripts on servers.</p>
<h2 id="advantages-of-cron-jobs">Advantages of Cron Jobs</h2>
<ol>
<li>
<p><strong>Scheduled Automation</strong>
   Cron jobs allow you to schedule repetitive tasks efficiently, whether they need to run every minute, daily, weekly, or at custom intervals.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Flexible Scheduling</strong>
   Cron's syntax supports precise configurations, such as running a task only during office hours or on specific days of the month. However, for very complex schedules, like "the first Monday every three months", the syntax can become cumbersome, making alternatives worth considering for such scenarios.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Lightweight and Reliable</strong>
   Cron is lightweight and consumes minimal system resources, which makes it ideal for even low-powered servers.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Set-It-and-Forget-It</strong>
   Once set up, cron jobs run silently in the background, requiring little to no manual intervention.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Built-In and Widely Available</strong>
   Cron jobs are widely used because <code>cron</code> or its equivalents are often available in Unix-based systems. However, not all distributions come with it pre-installed, especially those modernized with systemd. In those cases, alternatives like <code>systemd-timers</code> might be the default for scheduling tasks, though they are not direct replacements for <code>cron</code> and may behave differently in certain scenarios.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Adaptable to Broad Use Cases</strong>
   Cron jobs can handle a variety of tasks, from simple file cleanups to monitoring processes and sending notifications.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="disadvantages-of-cron-jobs">Disadvantages of Cron Jobs</h2>
<ol>
<li>
<p><strong>Complex Syntax</strong>
   While cron syntax is powerful, its learning curve is a drawback for beginners. A small mistake can lead to a misconfigured job or, worse, unexpected outcomes. Tools like <a href="https://crontab.guru">crontab.guru</a> allow users to generate and validate cron expressions visually, which can ease the learning curve.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Static and Rigid Configuration</strong>
   Cron jobs are predefined. They don't adapt to dynamic conditions, such as waiting for a dependency to complete or adjusting for time zone differences.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Time Zone Limitations</strong>
   Since cron jobs run based on the server's clock, tasks scheduled across multiple time zones require extra effort to configure correctly. Using tools like <code>systemd-timers</code> or third-party schedulers can simplify managing time zones, as they often have better support for time-based triggers and daylight saving adjustments.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>No Dependency Management</strong>
   Cron operates in isolation. It won't check whether the required services or conditions are in place before executing a task.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Not Ideal for Scaling</strong>
   As systems grow and require distributed task execution, cron jobs can become cumbersome. In such cases, tools like Kubernetes CronJobs or Celery are often better suited.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="a-human-centric-view">A Human-Centric View</h2>
<h3 id="why-some-people-love-cron-jobs">Why Some People Love Cron Jobs</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Simplicity and Accessibility</strong>: Cron jobs are straightforward to use once you're familiar with the syntax. They provide a no-frills way to automate everyday tasks without additional tools or software.</li>
<li><strong>Set It and Forget It</strong>: Knowing that a task will occur at a specific time, without needing manual intervention, brings comfort. For example, nightly backups or log rotations are worry-free once configured.</li>
<li><strong>Quick Wins</strong>: Cron jobs are perfect for quickly automating something small. Whether it's generating a daily report or cleaning temporary files, they let you get things done efficiently.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="why-cron-jobs-might-not-be-for-everyone">Why Cron Jobs Might Not Be for Everyone</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>A False Sense of Security</strong>: One of my biggest reservations with cron jobs is how easy it is to assume that everything is working just fine. Without proper monitoring, you might only realize a failure has occurred when it's too late to prevent damage.</li>
<li><strong>A Shortcut Culture</strong>: Cron jobs can sometimes feel like a band-aid solution rather than addressing root issues. For example, instead of solving a problem directly, someone might create a cron job to restart a failing service every 10 minutes. This approach creates technical debt, as the underlying issue remains unresolved and could lead to a larger failure over time.</li>
<li><strong>Out of Sight, Out of Mind</strong>: Since cron jobs run quietly in the background, they're easy to forget. Over time, schedules pile up, documentation is neglected, and you're left with something no one fully understands.</li>
<li><strong>Limited Debugging</strong>: Troubleshooting cron jobs can be frustrating if they aren't configured to log and/or email errors.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="cron-jobs-done-right-striking-a-balance">Cron Jobs Done Right: Striking a Balance</h2>
<p>The reality is, cron jobs are neither inherently good nor bad; their value depends entirely on how you approach and manage them. Here are a few key principles I've found helpful to make sure cron jobs remain an asset rather than a liability:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p><strong>Monitor Carefully</strong>: Never assume a cron job is running perfectly. Use logging and alerts to detect failures or issues early.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Documentation Matters</strong>: Every cron job should be well-documented. Not just what it does, but also why it exists. This way, if something goes wrong (or evolves), the team can address it.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Address Root Causes</strong>: Resist the temptation to use cron as a bypass or patch. If a job exists to fix something repeatedly, dig deeper to resolve the root cause.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Cron jobs continue to play a vital role in task automation. They're reliable, lightweight, and great for quick, repetitive tasks. But they also demand responsibility. When used carelessly or in a complex environment, they can mask issues, complicate debugging, and create more problems down the line.</p>
<p>Automation should streamline processes, not create blind spots or hidden risks in your systems. When cron jobs are paired with proper monitoring, documentation, and a mindset for solving underlying problems, they remain highly valuable for workflow efficiency. But, they're just one tool in the broader task automation toolkit. For complex or scaling environments, alternatives may bring better long-term results without sacrificing accountability or system health.</p>
<hr>
<p>Thank you for reading!</p>
<p>This article was written by Ramiro Gómez using open source software and the assistance of AI tools. While I strive to ensure accurate information, please verify any details independently before taking action. For more articles, visit the <a href="https://geeksta.net/geeklog/">Geeklog on geeksta.net</a>.</p>        ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title><![CDATA[Image Prompt Creator: Generate AI Prompts from Images]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[https://geeksta.net/geeklog/image-prompt-creator-introduction/]]></link>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>Discover Image Prompt Creator, an AI tool that converts images into structured prompts for use with image generation models, such as Ideogram and Midjourney. Simple, fast, and efficient.</p><img src="/img/geeklog/image-prompt-creator.png" alt="Preview Image">]]></description>
        <guid><![CDATA[https://geeksta.net/geeklog/image-prompt-creator-introduction/]]></guid>
        <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2025 21:18:59 </pubDate>
        <content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <p>Writing effective prompts for AI image-generation models can often be a time-consuming task. <a href="https://agent.ai/agent/image-prompt-creator?referrer=yaph">Image Prompt Creator</a> has been developed to streamline this process by using advanced AI to turn uploaded images into structured, descriptive prompts.</p>
<p>The tool provides an efficient way to create detailed prompts for models such as ChatGPT, Flux, Ideogram, Midjourney, and Stable Diffusion. By analyzing the key elements of an image, it generates a text-based description suitable for reproducing, modifying, or drawing inspiration from the visual content.</p>
<h2 id="how-it-works">How It Works</h2>
<p><img alt="Portrait of a young female samurai in traditional Japanese armor, wearing a white kimono with intricate patterns and a red obi sash, her hair neatly tied up with red and black ornaments. She has a calm and determined expression, with a katana sword sheathed at her side. The background is minimalist and light grey, emphasizing the subject. The image is rendered in a hyper-realistic style, with soft, diffused lighting and a muted, monochromatic color palette accented by subtle reds and metallics. The composition is a waist-up view, capturing detailed textures and the serene, stoic mood of the character." src="/img/geeklog/image-prompt-creator.png" /></p>
<p>Image Prompt Creator uses visual analysis and language modeling to examine the uploaded image. The tool identifies core characteristics and translates them into a prompt designed for AI image generators. The generated prompt includes key details, such as:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Subject &amp; Key Elements:</strong> Identifies the primary focus and notable objects or features.</li>
<li><strong>Artistic Style:</strong> Describes the artistic approach (e.g., realism, abstract, or digital painting).</li>
<li><strong>Composition &amp; Layout:</strong> Details how elements are arranged within the frame.</li>
<li><strong>Color Palette &amp; Lighting:</strong> Highlights prominent colors and lighting nuances.</li>
<li><strong>Mood &amp; Ambience:</strong> Captures the image's overall tone or feel.</li>
<li><strong>Perspective or Camera Angle:</strong> Notes the viewpoint or framing of the image.</li>
</ul>
<p>This structured prompt can then be used as-is or further customized to suit creative needs.</p>
<h2 id="practical-applications">Practical Applications</h2>
<p>Image Prompt Creator is designed for a wide range of users, from professionals to hobbyists. Some of the common use cases include:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Designers:</strong> Develop or refine visual concepts efficiently.</li>
<li><strong>Artists:</strong> Experiment with styles or recreate desired aesthetic themes.</li>
<li><strong>Content Creators:</strong> Maintain consistent branding across platforms.</li>
<li><strong>Educators &amp; Researchers:</strong> Facilitate studies in generative AI with detailed prompts.</li>
<li><strong>Print-on-Demand Entrepreneurs:</strong> Reimagine existing designs or brainstorm new ideas.</li>
<li><strong>AI Art Enthusiasts:</strong> Explore creative experiments with ease.</li>
</ul>
<p>The tool is particularly suited to tasks where clarity, consistency, and creative exploration are required.</p>
<h2 id="getting-started">Getting Started</h2>
<p>The process for using Image Prompt Creator is simple:</p>
<ol>
<li>Visit <a href="https://agent.ai/agent/image-prompt-creator?referrer=yaph">Image Prompt Creator</a>.</li>
<li>Upload any image you'd like to analyze.</li>
<li>Receive a detailed, AI-generated prompt in seconds.</li>
</ol>
<p>The interface is intuitive and accessible, making it easy to use regardless of technical skill level.</p>
<h2 id="why-choose-image-prompt-creator">Why Choose Image Prompt Creator?</h2>
<p>This tool offers several practical benefits, including:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Time Efficiency:</strong> Eliminates the need to manually craft descriptive prompts.</li>
<li><strong>Consistency:</strong> Ensures cohesive results for visual projects.</li>
<li><strong>Enhanced Creativity:</strong> Provides a starting point for new ideas based on existing images.</li>
<li><strong>Simplicity:</strong> Requires no advanced knowledge to use effectively.</li>
</ul>
<p>By automating parts of the creative process, Image Prompt Creator allows users to focus more on their artistic vision or design goals.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Image Prompt Creator is a thoughtful resource for anyone working with AI image-generation tools. It offers a straightforward way to turn inspiration from images into actionable prompts, supporting a variety of creative workflows.</p>
<p>Whether the goal is to create professional designs, explore artistic ideas, or study generative AI techniques, this tool provides a dependable solution for simplifying the process.</p>
<p>Explore its features today by visiting <a href="https://agent.ai/agent/image-prompt-creator?referrer=yaph">Image Prompt Creator on Agent.ai</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p>Thank you for reading!</p>
<p>This article was written by Ramiro Gómez using open source software and the assistance of AI tools. While I strive to ensure accurate information, please verify any details independently before taking action. For more articles, visit the <a href="https://geeksta.net/geeklog/">Geeklog on geeksta.net</a>.</p>        ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title><![CDATA[Server Failover: A Guide for System Administrators]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[https://geeksta.net/geeklog/server-failover-a-guide-for-system-administrators/]]></link>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>Learn server failover types, when to use automatic vs manual failover, and best practices for sysadmins. Essential guide to minimize downtime and ensure high availability.</p>]]></description>
        <guid><![CDATA[https://geeksta.net/geeklog/server-failover-a-guide-for-system-administrators/]]></guid>
        <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 22:33:55 </pubDate>
        <content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <p>Downtime is the enemy of every business operating online. When servers fail, revenue stops flowing, customers grow frustrated, and your company's reputation takes a hit. This is where server failover becomes your safety net, ensuring continuous service even when things go wrong.</p>
<h2 id="what-is-server-failover">What is Server Failover?</h2>
<p>Server failover is the process of automatically or manually switching from a primary server to a backup server when the primary system becomes unavailable. Think of it as having a backup generator that kicks in during a power outage - your services continue running while the main system gets repaired.</p>
<p>The goal is simple: maintain service availability and minimize disruption to end users. When implemented correctly, failover can reduce downtime from hours to mere minutes or seconds.</p>
<h2 id="understanding-failover-architecture">Understanding Failover Architecture</h2>
<p>Before diving into specific types, it's important to understand the basic components of a failover system:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Primary Server</strong>: The main system handling regular traffic</li>
<li><strong>Secondary Server</strong>: The backup system ready to take over</li>
<li><strong>Load Balancer</strong>: Directs traffic between servers</li>
<li><strong>Health Monitoring</strong>: Continuously checks server status</li>
<li><strong>Shared Storage</strong>: Ensures data consistency across servers</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="types-of-server-failover">Types of Server Failover</h2>
<h3 id="1-automatic-failover">1. Automatic Failover</h3>
<p>Automatic failover systems monitor your primary server continuously and switch to backup systems without human intervention when problems are detected.</p>
<h4 id="how-it-works">How it works:</h4>
<ul>
<li>Monitoring agents check server health every few seconds</li>
<li>When the primary server fails predefined health checks, the system triggers failover</li>
<li>Traffic automatically redirects to the backup server</li>
<li>The switch typically happens within 30 seconds to 2 minutes</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="best-for">Best for:</h4>
<ul>
<li>Critical applications requiring 24/7 availability</li>
<li>Systems without dedicated monitoring staff</li>
<li>Environments where quick response time is essential</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="2-manual-failover">2. Manual Failover</h3>
<p>Manual failover requires human intervention to initiate the switch from primary to backup servers.</p>
<h4 id="how-it-works_1">How it works:</h4>
<ul>
<li>Administrators receive alerts about server issues</li>
<li>Team evaluates the situation and decides whether to failover</li>
<li>Manual steps are executed to redirect traffic</li>
<li>Process can take anywhere from minutes to hours</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="best-for_1">Best for:</h4>
<ul>
<li>Planned maintenance windows</li>
<li>Non-critical applications where brief downtime is acceptable</li>
<li>Organizations preferring human oversight for major changes</li>
<li>Testing disaster recovery procedures</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="failover-configuration-types">Failover Configuration Types</h2>
<h3 id="active-passive-hot-standby">Active-Passive (Hot Standby)</h3>
<p>In this setup, one server actively handles all traffic while the backup server remains on standby, ready to take over immediately.</p>
<h4 id="characteristics">Characteristics:</h4>
<ul>
<li>Primary server handles 100% of traffic</li>
<li>Backup server stays synchronized but doesn't serve requests</li>
<li>Fastest failover time (typically under 60 seconds)</li>
<li>Higher resource cost due to idle backup server</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="when-to-use">When to use:</h4>
<ul>
<li>Mission-critical applications</li>
<li>When you need the fastest possible recovery time</li>
<li>Applications that can't handle load balancing complexity</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="active-active-load-balanced">Active-Active (Load Balanced)</h3>
<p>Both servers actively handle traffic simultaneously, sharing the workload between them.</p>
<h4 id="characteristics_1">Characteristics:</h4>
<ul>
<li>Traffic distributed across multiple servers</li>
<li>If one server fails, the remaining server(s) handle increased load</li>
<li>Better resource utilization</li>
<li>More complex configuration and management</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="when-to-use_1">When to use:</h4>
<ul>
<li>High-traffic applications</li>
<li>When you want to maximize resource efficiency</li>
<li>Applications designed for distributed processing</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="cold-standby">Cold Standby</h3>
<p>The backup server remains powered off until needed, requiring manual startup during failover.</p>
<h4 id="characteristics_2">Characteristics:</h4>
<ul>
<li>Lowest cost option</li>
<li>Longest recovery time (30 minutes to several hours)</li>
<li>Requires manual intervention</li>
<li>Higher risk of backup server issues</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="when-to-use_2">When to use:</h4>
<ul>
<li>Budget-constrained environments</li>
<li>Non-critical applications</li>
<li>When extended downtime is acceptable</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="when-to-choose-each-type">When to Choose Each Type</h2>
<h3 id="choose-automatic-failover-when">Choose Automatic Failover When:</h3>
<ul>
<li>Your application generates significant revenue that downtime would impact</li>
<li>You lack 24/7 monitoring staff</li>
<li>Recovery time objectives are under 5 minutes</li>
<li>You operate in industries with strict uptime requirements (finance, healthcare)</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="choose-manual-failover-when">Choose Manual Failover When:</h3>
<ul>
<li>You have experienced staff available for monitoring</li>
<li>Cost is a primary concern</li>
<li>Applications aren't mission-critical</li>
<li>You prefer human oversight for major system changes</li>
<li>Planned maintenance is your primary use case</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="choose-active-passive-when">Choose Active-Passive When:</h3>
<ul>
<li>You need the fastest possible recovery time</li>
<li>Your application doesn't support load balancing</li>
<li>Data consistency is critical</li>
<li>Budget allows for dedicated backup resources</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="choose-active-active-when">Choose Active-Active When:</h3>
<ul>
<li>You have high traffic volumes</li>
<li>Your application supports distributed processing</li>
<li>You want maximum resource efficiency</li>
<li>You can handle the complexity of load balancing</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="best-practices-for-system-administrators">Best Practices for System Administrators</h2>
<h3 id="1-design-and-planning">1. Design and Planning</h3>
<h4 id="document-everything">Document Everything</h4>
<p>Create detailed runbooks that include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Step-by-step failover procedures</li>
<li>Contact information for key personnel</li>
<li>System credentials and access methods</li>
<li>Rollback procedures</li>
<li>Expected recovery times</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="define-clear-objectives">Define Clear Objectives</h4>
<p>Establish specific metrics:</p>
<ul>
<li>Recovery Time Objective (RTO): Maximum acceptable downtime</li>
<li>Recovery Point Objective (RPO): Maximum acceptable data loss</li>
<li>Service level agreements with stakeholders</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="2-implementation-guidelines">2. Implementation Guidelines</h3>
<h4 id="ensure-data-synchronization">Ensure Data Synchronization</h4>
<ul>
<li>Implement real-time data replication between primary and backup servers</li>
<li>Use database clustering or replication features</li>
<li>Regularly verify data consistency</li>
<li>Test backup data integrity</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="configure-proper-monitoring">Configure Proper Monitoring</h4>
<ul>
<li>Set up comprehensive health checks beyond simple ping tests</li>
<li>Monitor application-level functionality, not just server availability</li>
<li>Configure alerting with appropriate escalation procedures</li>
<li>Use multiple monitoring tools for redundancy</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="network-configuration">Network Configuration</h4>
<ul>
<li>Use DNS with low TTL values for faster failover</li>
<li>Implement load balancers with health checking capabilities</li>
<li>Configure network routing to support quick traffic redirection</li>
<li>Ensure backup servers have adequate network capacity</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="3-testing-and-validation">3. Testing and Validation</h3>
<h4 id="regular-failover-testing">Regular Failover Testing</h4>
<p>Conduct scheduled tests:</p>
<ul>
<li>Monthly automated failover tests during low-traffic periods</li>
<li>Quarterly full disaster recovery drills</li>
<li>Annual comprehensive system testing</li>
<li>Document all test results and improvement areas</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="performance-validation">Performance Validation</h4>
<ul>
<li>Verify backup systems can handle full production load</li>
<li>Test application functionality after failover</li>
<li>Measure actual recovery times versus objectives</li>
<li>Validate data integrity post-failover</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="4-operational-excellence">4. Operational Excellence</h3>
<h4 id="staff-training">Staff Training</h4>
<ul>
<li>Train multiple team members on failover procedures</li>
<li>Conduct regular training sessions and simulations</li>
<li>Maintain updated contact lists and escalation procedures</li>
<li>Cross-train staff to avoid single points of failure</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="continuous-improvement">Continuous Improvement</h4>
<ul>
<li>Review failover events for lessons learned</li>
<li>Update procedures based on new requirements</li>
<li>Monitor industry best practices and new technologies</li>
<li>Regularly assess and update hardware and software</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="communication-planning">Communication Planning</h4>
<ul>
<li>Establish clear communication channels during incidents</li>
<li>Prepare templates for customer notifications</li>
<li>Define roles and responsibilities during failover events</li>
<li>Create status page procedures for transparency</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="5-security-considerations">5. Security Considerations</h3>
<h4 id="access-control">Access Control</h4>
<ul>
<li>Implement strict access controls for failover systems</li>
<li>Use multi-factor authentication for administrative access</li>
<li>Regularly audit access permissions</li>
<li>Maintain separate credentials for backup systems</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="security-monitoring">Security Monitoring</h4>
<ul>
<li>Monitor backup systems for security threats</li>
<li>Keep security patches current on all systems</li>
<li>Implement intrusion detection on failover infrastructure</li>
<li>Regularly scan for vulnerabilities</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="common-pitfalls-to-avoid">Common Pitfalls to Avoid</h2>
<h3 id="split-brain-scenarios">Split-Brain Scenarios</h3>
<p>Prevent situations where both primary and backup servers think they're active:</p>
<ul>
<li>Implement proper cluster management software</li>
<li>Use shared storage with locking mechanisms</li>
<li>Configure proper network isolation</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="inadequate-resource-planning">Inadequate Resource Planning</h3>
<p>Ensure backup systems can handle production loads:</p>
<ul>
<li>Size backup servers appropriately</li>
<li>Account for peak traffic scenarios</li>
<li>Plan for degraded performance during failover</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="neglecting-dependencies">Neglecting Dependencies</h3>
<p>Consider all system dependencies:</p>
<ul>
<li>Database connections and replication</li>
<li>External service integrations</li>
<li>Network and DNS configurations</li>
<li>Third-party service dependencies</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="measuring-success">Measuring Success</h2>
<p>Track key metrics to evaluate your failover effectiveness:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Mean Time to Recovery (MTTR)</strong>: Average time to restore service</li>
<li><strong>Mean Time Between Failures (MTBF)</strong>: Average time between system failures</li>
<li><strong>Availability Percentage</strong>: Uptime percentage over specific periods</li>
<li><strong>Successful Failover Rate</strong>: Percentage of successful automated failovers</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Server failover is not just a technical requirement - it's a business necessity in today's always-on digital world. The key to successful implementation lies in understanding your specific requirements, choosing the right failover type, and following proven best practices.</p>
<p>Remember that failover systems are only as good as your preparation, testing, and maintenance efforts. Regular testing, comprehensive documentation, and continuous improvement will ensure your failover systems work when you need them most.</p>
<p>Start with a clear assessment of your requirements, implement appropriate solutions gradually, and always prioritize testing and documentation. Your future self (and your users) will thank you when the inevitable server failure occurs and your systems seamlessly continue operating.</p>
<hr>
<p>Thank you for reading!</p>
<p>This article was written by Ramiro Gómez using open source software and the assistance of AI tools. While I strive to ensure accurate information, please verify any details independently before taking action. For more articles, visit the <a href="https://geeksta.net/geeklog/">Geeklog on geeksta.net</a>.</p>        ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title><![CDATA[Fixing Dovecot Diffie-Hellman Parameter Error]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[https://geeksta.net/geeklog/fixing-dovecot-diffie-hellman-parameter-error/]]></link>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>Learn how to fix Dovecot's Diffie-Hellman key exchange requested SSL error by generating DH parameters with OpenSSL and configuring ssl_dh properly.</p>]]></description>
        <guid><![CDATA[https://geeksta.net/geeklog/fixing-dovecot-diffie-hellman-parameter-error/]]></guid>
        <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 12:58:59 </pubDate>
        <content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <p>This guide helps you resolve SSL/TLS connection issues in Dovecot IMAP server when Diffie-Hellman parameters are missing. The error prevents secure email client connections and requires generating cryptographic parameters and updating the Dovecot configuration.</p>
<h2 id="the-error">The Error</h2>
<p>When you see this in your Dovecot logs:</p>
<pre><code class="language-text">dovecot: imap-login: Error: Diffie-Hellman key exchange requested, but no DH parameters provided. Set ssl_dh=&lt;/path/to/dh.pem
</code></pre>
<p>This means Dovecot needs DH parameters for SSL/TLS connections but can't find the required file.</p>
<h2 id="solution">Solution</h2>
<h3 id="1-generate-dh-parameters">1. Generate DH Parameters</h3>
<pre><code class="language-bash"># 2048-bit (recommended - faster generation, still secure)
openssl dhparam -out /etc/ssl/certs/dh.pem 2048

# OR 4096-bit (higher security, much slower generation)
openssl dhparam -out /etc/ssl/certs/dh.pem 4096
</code></pre>
<p><strong>Important:</strong> The parameter order matters! The <code>-out</code> option must come before the bit size.</p>
<p><strong>Note:</strong> Generation takes time, much more much longer for 4096-bit than for 2048-bit. This is normal as it's generating cryptographically secure prime numbers.</p>
<h3 id="2-configure-dovecot">2. Configure Dovecot</h3>
<p>Add this line to your Dovecot configuration (usually <code>/etc/dovecot/dovecot.conf</code> or <code>/etc/dovecot/conf.d/10-ssl.conf</code>):</p>
<pre><code class="language-text">ssl_dh = &lt;/etc/ssl/certs/dh.pem
</code></pre>
<h3 id="3-restart-dovecot">3. Restart Dovecot</h3>
<pre><code class="language-bash">systemctl restart dovecot
</code></pre>
<h2 id="key-points">Key Points</h2>
<ul>
<li>2048-bit is sufficient for most security requirements and generates much faster</li>
<li>4096-bit provides higher security but takes significantly longer to generate</li>
<li>Parameter order is critical in the openssl command</li>
<li>Long Generation time is normal - the process is doing real cryptographic work</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>The Dovecot DH parameter error is resolved by generating cryptographic parameters with OpenSSL and configuring Dovecot to use them. Choose 2048-bit for faster generation or 4096-bit for enhanced security. After configuration, restart Dovecot to enable secure IMAP connections with proper Diffie-Hellman key exchange.</p>
<hr>
<p>Thank you for reading!</p>
<p>This article was written by Ramiro Gómez using open source software and the assistance of AI tools. While I strive to ensure accurate information, please verify any details independently before taking action. For more articles, visit the <a href="https://geeksta.net/geeklog/">Geeklog on geeksta.net</a>.</p>        ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title><![CDATA[How to Search and View mbox Email Archives]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[https://geeksta.net/geeklog/how-to-search-and-view-mbox-email-archives/]]></link>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>Learn how to efficiently search, navigate, and extract emails from mbox files using mutt and other command-line tools in this comprehensive step-by-step tutorial.</p>]]></description>
        <guid><![CDATA[https://geeksta.net/geeklog/how-to-search-and-view-mbox-email-archives/]]></guid>
        <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 12:28:26 </pubDate>
        <content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <p>The mbox format is one of the oldest and most widely used mailbox formats in Unix-like systems. Unlike more modern formats that store each message as a separate file, mbox concatenates all emails into a single text file, with special separator lines starting with "From " (often called "From_" lines) to mark the beginning of each message. This tutorial provides detailed instructions on how to effectively view and search through these files.</p>
<h2 id="understanding-mbox-files">Understanding mbox Files</h2>
<p>An mbox file is essentially a plain text file containing multiple email messages. The structure looks like this:</p>
<pre><code class="language-text">From sender@example.com Wed Jan 10 12:00:00 2025
Subject: First email subject
From: sender@example.com
To: recipient@example.com

Content of first email...

From another@example.com Thu Jan 11 15:30:00 2025
Subject: Second email subject
From: another@example.com
To: recipient@example.com

Content of second email...
</code></pre>
<p>While you could technically view this with any text editor, specialized tools provide a much better experience by properly parsing and displaying each message as a separate entity.</p>
<h2 id="basic-viewing-with-mutt">Basic Viewing with mutt</h2>
<p><a href="http://www.mutt.org/">Mutt</a> is a powerful terminal-based email client that handles mbox files exceptionally well. It's lightweight, fast, and provides an intuitive interface for navigating through email collections.</p>
<h3 id="opening-an-mbox-file">Opening an mbox file:</h3>
<pre><code class="language-bash">mutt -f /path/to/your/mbox_file
</code></pre>
<p>This opens the mbox file in mutt, displaying a list of all emails in an index view. Mutt will properly parse the mbox format, showing each email as a separate item with sender, date, and subject information.</p>
<h3 id="navigation-in-mutt">Navigation in mutt:</h3>
<p>Once inside mutt, you can navigate through emails using these keyboard shortcuts:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>j/k</strong>: Move down/up in the email list (also works with arrow keys)</li>
<li><strong>Enter</strong>: Open the selected email to view its full content</li>
<li><strong>q</strong>: Return to the email list when viewing an email</li>
<li><strong>q</strong>: Exit mutt completely when viewing the email list</li>
<li><strong>Page Up/Down</strong>: Scroll through long emails when viewing a message</li>
<li><strong>Space</strong>: Page down when reading a message</li>
<li><strong>-</strong>: Page up when reading a message</li>
<li><strong>Home/End</strong>: Jump to the beginning/end of an email</li>
<li><strong>\&lt;</strong> and <strong>&gt;</strong>: Jump to the first and last email in the list</li>
<li><strong>?</strong>: Show help screen with all available commands</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="marking-and-tagging-emails">Marking and tagging emails:</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>t</strong>: Tag/untag the current message (useful for batch operations)</li>
<li><strong>T</strong>: Tag messages matching a pattern</li>
<li><strong>;</strong>: Apply the next command to all tagged messages</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="advanced-searching-in-mutt">Advanced Searching in mutt</h2>
<p>Mutt provides powerful search capabilities that are particularly useful when dealing with large mbox files.</p>
<h3 id="quick-search">Quick search:</h3>
<ol>
<li>Press <code>/</code> while in the email list</li>
<li>Type your search pattern (e.g., <code>^Subject:.*Invoice-2025</code>)</li>
<li>Press Enter to jump to the first match</li>
<li>Press <code>n</code> to find the next match or <code>N</code> for the previous match</li>
</ol>
<p>The search above looks for "Invoice-2025" anywhere in the subject line. The <code>^Subject:</code> part ensures we're looking in the subject header.</p>
<h3 id="pattern-based-searching-and-limiting">Pattern-based searching and limiting:</h3>
<p>Mutt offers a more powerful search mechanism using patterns:</p>
<ol>
<li>Press <code>l</code> (lowercase L) to limit the view</li>
<li>Enter a pattern like <code>~s "Invoice-2025"</code> to show only emails with that subject</li>
<li>To clear the limit and see all emails again, press <code>l</code> followed by <code>all</code> or just <code>^L</code> (Ctrl+L)</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="common-search-patterns">Common search patterns:</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Subject search</strong>: <code>~s "Invoice-2025"</code></li>
<li><strong>From/sender search</strong>: <code>~f "john@example.com"</code></li>
<li><strong>To/recipient search</strong>: <code>~t "accounting@company.com"</code></li>
<li><strong>Content/body search</strong>: <code>~b "urgent payment"</code></li>
<li><strong>Date search</strong>: <code>~d &gt;1w</code> (emails newer than 1 week)</li>
<li><strong>Date range</strong>: <code>~d 01/01/2025-31/01/2025</code> (emails from January 2025)</li>
<li><strong>Has attachment</strong>: <code>~h "Content-Type: multipart"</code></li>
</ul>
<p>You can combine patterns with logical operators:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>AND</strong>: <code>~f "john" ~s "Invoice"</code></li>
<li><strong>OR</strong>: <code>~f "john" | ~f "jane"</code></li>
<li><strong>NOT</strong>: <code>! ~f "spam@example.com"</code></li>
</ul>
<h3 id="search-on-startup">Search on startup:</h3>
<p>Launch mutt with a pre-defined search to immediately show relevant emails:</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">mutt -f /path/to/mbox_file -e &quot;push /^Subject:.*Invoice-2025&lt;enter&gt;&quot;
</code></pre>
<p>Or to limit the view immediately upon startup:</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">mutt -f /path/to/mbox_file -e &quot;push l~s Invoice-2025&lt;enter&gt;&quot;
</code></pre>
<h2 id="alternative-tools-for-working-with-mbox-files">Alternative Tools for Working with mbox Files</h2>
<p>While mutt is the recommended tool, there are other approaches that can be useful in certain scenarios.</p>
<h3 id="using-grep-for-quick-inspection">Using grep for quick inspection:</h3>
<p>For a quick peek at emails matching a pattern without opening a full email client:</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">grep -A 10 -B 2 &quot;Subject: Invoice-2025&quot; /path/to/mbox_file | less
</code></pre>
<p>This shows 2 lines before and 10 lines after each occurrence of "Subject: Invoice-2025". Adjust the numbers as needed to see more or less context.</p>
<p>For case-insensitive search:</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">grep -i -A 10 -B 2 &quot;subject: invoice&quot; /path/to/mbox_file | less
</code></pre>
<h3 id="using-formail-from-procmail-package">Using formail (from procmail package):</h3>
<p>The formail utility can extract specific emails from an mbox file:</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">formail -s grep &quot;^Subject:.*Invoice-2025&quot; &lt; mbox_file &gt; matching_emails.mbox
</code></pre>
<p>This creates a new mbox file containing only the emails that match the pattern. You can then view this smaller file:</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">mutt -f matching_emails.mbox
</code></pre>
<p>For more complex filtering:</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">formail -s awk '/^Subject:.*Invoice/ &amp;&amp; /^From:.*john/' &lt; mbox_file &gt; filtered.mbox
</code></pre>
<p>This extracts emails with "Invoice" in the subject AND from someone named "john".</p>
<h2 id="practical-tips-for-working-with-mbox-files">Practical Tips for Working with mbox Files</h2>
<p><strong>Create a temporary .muttrc file for complex operations</strong>:</p>
<pre><code class="language-text">echo &quot;set sort=date-received&quot; &gt; temp_muttrc
mutt -F temp_muttrc -f mbox_file
</code></pre>
<p><strong>Backup before modifying</strong>: Always make a copy of your mbox file before performing operations that might modify it.</p>
<p><strong>Extract a single email</strong>: To save a specific email as a separate file:</p>
<pre><code class="language-text">formail -s procmail &lt; mbox_file
</code></pre>
<p>(Use this with a .procmailrc file that defines extraction rules)</p>
<p><strong>Split large mbox files</strong>: For exceptionally large mbox files, consider:</p>
<pre><code class="language-text">csplit -f email- mbox_file '/^From /' '{*}'
</code></pre>
<p>This creates separate files for each email.</p>
<p><strong>Convert to other formats</strong>: To convert to Maildir format:</p>
<pre><code class="language-text">mb2md -s /path/to/mbox -d /path/to/maildir
</code></pre>
<p>Remember that mbox files are simple text files, so any text processing tool can work with them, but mail-specific tools like mutt will provide the best viewing experience by properly parsing and formatting the messages.</p>
<hr>
<p>Thank you for reading!</p>
<p>This article was written by Ramiro Gómez using open source software and the assistance of AI tools. While I strive to ensure accurate information, please verify any details independently before taking action. For more articles, visit the <a href="https://geeksta.net/geeklog/">Geeklog on geeksta.net</a>.</p>        ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title><![CDATA[Troubleshooting Database Load Issues on Debian Linux: A Practical Guide]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[https://geeksta.net/geeklog/troubleshooting-database-load-issues-on-debian-linux/]]></link>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>Learn practical steps to diagnose and resolve high database load issues on Debian Linux servers. This guide covers essential monitoring tools, query optimization techniques, and proactive measures to keep your databases running smoothly.</p>]]></description>
        <guid><![CDATA[https://geeksta.net/geeklog/troubleshooting-database-load-issues-on-debian-linux/]]></guid>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Apr 2025 19:22:07 </pubDate>
        <content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <p>As a database administrator or system engineer, you've likely encountered the dreaded alert informing you about critical load on the database server. In this guide, I'll walk you through a systematic approach to diagnose and resolve high database load issues on Debian Linux servers.</p>
<h2 id="understanding-the-problem-what-causes-high-database-load">Understanding the Problem: What Causes High Database Load?</h2>
<p>Before diving into troubleshooting, let's understand what we're looking for. Database load issues typically stem from one or more of these factors:</p>
<ul>
<li>Poorly optimized queries consuming excessive resources</li>
<li>Insufficient system resources (CPU, memory, disk I/O)</li>
<li>Connection bottlenecks or connection pool exhaustion</li>
<li>Inadequate database configuration</li>
<li>Background processes competing for resources</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="your-first-response-initial-assessment">Your First Response: Initial Assessment</h2>
<p>When you first receive that critical alert, don't panic. Start with these essential commands to get a quick overview of the situation:</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash"># Get an overview of system resource usage
htop

# Check disk I/O statistics
iostat -xz 1

# View memory statistics
free -h
vmstat 1
</code></pre>
<p>These commands will give you an immediate sense of whether you're dealing with CPU saturation, memory pressure, or I/O bottlenecks.</p>
<h2 id="database-specific-intelligence-gathering">Database-Specific Intelligence Gathering</h2>
<p>Now that you have a general understanding of the system state, it's time to look specifically at your database processes:</p>
<h3 id="for-mysqlmariadb">For MySQL/MariaDB:</h3>
<pre><code class="language-bash"># View current database processes
sudo mysqladmin processlist

# Check database status
sudo mysqladmin status

# Examine slow queries
sudo mysql -e &quot;SHOW FULL PROCESSLIST;&quot;
</code></pre>
<h3 id="for-postgresql">For PostgreSQL:</h3>
<pre><code class="language-bash"># View active connections and their states
sudo -u postgres psql -c &quot;SELECT count(*), state FROM pg_stat_activity GROUP BY state;&quot;

# Find long-running queries
sudo -u postgres psql -c &quot;SELECT pid, now() - query_start AS duration, query FROM pg_stat_activity WHERE state = 'active' ORDER BY duration DESC LIMIT 10;&quot;
</code></pre>
<h2 id="digging-deeper-detailed-investigation">Digging Deeper: Detailed Investigation</h2>
<p>If the initial assessment doesn't reveal the obvious culprit, it's time to dig deeper:</p>
<h3 id="analyzing-process-details">Analyzing Process Details</h3>
<p>If you've identified a specific process causing issues, examine it more closely:</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash"># Get detailed info on a specific process
ps -fp &lt;PID&gt;

# See what files the process has open
lsof -p &lt;PID&gt;

# View process resource limits
cat /proc/&lt;PID&gt;/limits
</code></pre>
<h3 id="examining-slow-queries">Examining Slow Queries</h3>
<p>Slow queries are often the root cause of database load issues:</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash"># For MySQL: Enable slow query log if not already enabled
sudo mysql -e &quot;SET GLOBAL slow_query_log = 'ON';&quot;
sudo mysql -e &quot;SET GLOBAL long_query_time = 1;&quot;

# Analyze slow query log
sudo mysqldumpslow /var/log/mysql/mysql-slow.log
</code></pre>
<h3 id="io-bottleneck-analysis">I/O Bottleneck Analysis</h3>
<p>If you suspect I/O bottlenecks:</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash"># Check for disk I/O issues
iostat -xz 1 10

# See which processes are causing most I/O
iotop
</code></pre>
<h2 id="the-fix-common-solutions-to-database-load-issues">The Fix: Common Solutions to Database Load Issues</h2>
<p>Based on your findings, here are some potential solutions:</p>
<h3 id="query-optimization">Query Optimization</h3>
<ul>
<li>Add missing indexes based on slow query analysis</li>
<li>Rewrite problematic queries identified in the slow query log</li>
<li>Consider using query caching where appropriate</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="database-configuration-tuning">Database Configuration Tuning</h3>
<pre><code class="language-bash"># MySQL: Key settings to examine
innodb_buffer_pool_size
max_connections
query_cache_size
innodb_log_file_size

# PostgreSQL: Important parameters
shared_buffers
work_mem
maintenance_work_mem
max_connections
</code></pre>
<h3 id="system-level-optimizations">System-Level Optimizations</h3>
<ul>
<li>Increase swap space if experiencing memory pressure</li>
<li>Consider I/O scheduling adjustments for database workloads</li>
<li>Implement connection pooling to manage connection loads</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="preventing-future-issues-proactive-monitoring">Preventing Future Issues: Proactive Monitoring</h2>
<p>To avoid being caught off guard again, implement these proactive measures:</p>
<ul>
<li>Set up Prometheus with database exporters</li>
<li>Create Grafana dashboards for visual monitoring</li>
<li>Implement automated alerting based on threshold values</li>
<li>Schedule regular database maintenance</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Troubleshooting high database load issues requires a methodical approach and the right tools. By following the steps outlined in this guide, you'll be able to quickly identify and resolve performance bottlenecks in your Debian Linux database servers.</p>
<p>Remember that the best solution to high load issues is preventing them in the first place through proper monitoring, regular maintenance, and proactive capacity planning.</p>
<hr>
<p>Thank you for reading!</p>
<p>This article was written by Ramiro Gómez using open source software and the assistance of AI tools. While I strive to ensure accurate information, please verify any details independently before taking action. For more articles, visit the <a href="https://geeksta.net/geeklog/">Geeklog on geeksta.net</a>.</p>        ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title><![CDATA[Checking DNS Zone Files]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[https://geeksta.net/geeklog/checking-dns-zone-files/]]></link>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>Learn why validating DNS zone files is critical for website reliability and email delivery. Discover practical tools and best practices to prevent costly DNS configuration errors.</p>]]></description>
        <guid><![CDATA[https://geeksta.net/geeklog/checking-dns-zone-files/]]></guid>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 12:14:08 </pubDate>
        <content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <p>DNS zone files are the backbone of domain name resolution on the internet. They contain the mappings between domain names and IP addresses, mail servers, and other critical infrastructure components. However, even a small syntax error in these files can lead to significant disruptions in service. In this post, we'll explore the importance of validating DNS zone files and some practical methods to do so.</p>
<h2 id="why-validate-zone-files">Why Validate Zone Files?</h2>
<p>A misconfigured zone file can cause various problems:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Website Unavailability</strong>: If A or AAAA records are incorrect, your website might become inaccessible.</li>
<li><strong>Email Delivery Failures</strong>: Incorrect MX records can prevent email delivery.</li>
<li><strong>Security Vulnerabilities</strong>: Improperly configured DNSSEC or SPF records might expose your domain to spoofing attacks.</li>
<li><strong>Propagation Delays</strong>: Errors might cause DNS propagation issues, leading to inconsistent behavior across the internet.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="tools-for-dns-zone-file-validation">Tools for DNS Zone File Validation</h2>
<h3 id="bind-utilities">BIND Utilities</h3>
<p>The BIND DNS server software provides excellent tools for checking zone files:</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash"># Basic syntax check
named-checkzone example.com /path/to/zonefile

# More verbose output
named-checkzone -v example.com /path/to/zonefile
</code></pre>
<p>The <code>named-compilezone</code> utility is another helpful tool that can convert between different zone file formats while checking for errors:</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">named-compilezone -o /dev/null example.com /path/to/zonefile
</code></pre>
<h3 id="online-validators">Online Validators</h3>
<p>Several online tools can help validate zone files, particularly useful if you don't have access to a server with BIND utilities installed.</p>
<h3 id="common-syntax-issues-to-watch-for">Common Syntax Issues to Watch For</h3>
<ol>
<li><strong>Missing Trailing Dots</strong>: Fully qualified domain names should end with a dot.</li>
<li><strong>Incorrect TTL Values</strong>: Time-to-live values must be numeric and reasonable.</li>
<li><strong>Record Format Errors</strong>: Each record type has specific formatting requirements.</li>
<li><strong>Long TXT Records</strong>: TXT records (like those for DKIM) might need to be split into multiple strings.</li>
<li><strong>SOA Record Errors</strong>: The Start of Authority record has a complex format that's easy to get wrong.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="best-practices">Best Practices</h2>
<ol>
<li><strong>Use Version Control</strong>: Track changes to your zone files.</li>
<li><strong>Test Before Deployment</strong>: Always validate before pushing changes to production.</li>
<li><strong>Maintain Documentation</strong>: Keep notes about your DNS configuration.</li>
<li><strong>Implement Automated Checks</strong>: Set up CI/CD pipelines to validate zone files automatically.</li>
<li><strong>Monitor DNS Health</strong>: Regularly check that your DNS is resolving correctly.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Taking the time to properly validate DNS zone files might seem tedious, but it's a crucial step in maintaining a reliable online presence. By catching errors before they propagate, you can avoid downtime and maintain trust with your users. Whether you're managing a personal blog or enterprise infrastructure, proper DNS hygiene is essential for a smooth-running internet presence.</p>
<hr>
<p>Thank you for reading!</p>
<p>This article was written by Ramiro Gómez using open source software and the assistance of AI tools. While I strive to ensure accurate information, please verify any details independently before taking action. For more articles, visit the <a href="https://geeksta.net/geeklog/">Geeklog on geeksta.net</a>.</p>        ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title><![CDATA[How to Use SD Cards for Backups on Linux]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[https://geeksta.net/geeklog/how-to-use-sd-cards-for-backups-on-linux/]]></link>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>A detailed guide on using SD cards for data backup on Linux. Learn formatting, mounting, and automating backups to ensure your files are safe and accessible.</p><img src="/img/geeklog/geeklog-sd-cards.webp" alt="Preview Image">]]></description>
        <guid><![CDATA[https://geeksta.net/geeklog/how-to-use-sd-cards-for-backups-on-linux/]]></guid>
        <pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 13:46:51 </pubDate>
        <content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <p>SD cards have come a long way from being simple storage for digital cameras. With capacities now reaching multiple terabytes, they present an attractive, portable backup solution. However, Linux users often encounter frustrating issues when attempting to leverage these pocket-sized storage powerhouses for serious backup purposes.</p>
<p>In this guide, we'll explore how to properly configure, verify, and utilize SD cards for reliable backups on Linux systems, avoiding common pitfalls that can lead to data loss and corruption.</p>
<h2 id="choosing-the-right-hardware">Choosing the Right Hardware</h2>
<h3 id="sd-card-selection">SD Card Selection</h3>
<p>Not all SD cards are created equal. When selecting a card for backup purposes, consider:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Capacity vs. Authenticity</strong>: That suspiciously cheap 1TB card might actually be a 32GB card hacked to report a larger size. When the card's real capacity is exceeded, data corruption occurs.</li>
<li><strong>Speed Classification</strong>: Look for UHS-I or UHS-II cards with higher speed ratings (V30, V60, V90) for backup operations.</li>
<li><strong>Endurance Rating</strong>: Cards designed for surveillance cameras or dashcams often have better write endurance, making them suitable for frequent backups.</li>
<li><strong>Brand Reliability</strong>: Stick with reputable brands like SanDisk, Samsung, Kingston, or Lexar from authorized retailers.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="card-readers-matter">Card Readers Matter</h3>
<p>A quality card reader can make the difference between successful backups and corrupted data:</p>
<ul>
<li>USB 3.0 or higher connectivity offers faster transfer speeds</li>
<li>Standalone powered readers provide more stable power than built-in laptop readers</li>
<li>Multi-card readers with dedicated SD slots often perform better than all-in-one solutions</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="verifying-your-sd-cards-authenticity">Verifying Your SD Card's Authenticity</h2>
<p>Before trusting your precious data to an SD card, verify its authenticity. The excellent open-source tool F3 (Fight Flash Fraud) makes this process straightforward:</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash"># Install F3
sudo apt install f3    # Debian/Ubuntu
sudo dnf install f3    # Fedora/RHEL
sudo pacman -S f3      # Arch Linux

# Write test files to fill the card
f3write /path/to/mounted/sdcard

# Verify the written data
f3read /path/to/mounted/sdcard
</code></pre>
<p>A genuine card will show consistent read/write speeds and verified capacity matching the advertised size. Counterfeit cards will report errors once the actual capacity is exceeded.</p>
<h2 id="choosing-the-optimal-filesystem">Choosing the Optimal Filesystem</h2>
<p>Your filesystem choice dramatically impacts backup reliability, especially with large-capacity cards:</p>
<h3 id="ext4-the-linux-native-option">ext4: The Linux Native Option</h3>
<pre><code class="language-bash">sudo mkfs.ext4 /dev/sdX
</code></pre>
<p><strong>Pros:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Journaling prevents corruption during unexpected disconnects</li>
<li>Excellent handling of many small files</li>
<li>Best performance on Linux systems</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Cons:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Limited compatibility with other operating systems</li>
<li>Requires additional software for Windows/macOS access</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="ntfs-the-windows-friendly-option">NTFS: The Windows-Friendly Option</h3>
<pre><code class="language-bash">sudo mkfs.ntfs -f /dev/sdX  # -f performs a quick format
</code></pre>
<p><strong>Pros:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Good cross-platform compatibility</li>
<li>Handles large files and large volumes well</li>
<li>No practical file size limitations</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Cons:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Write performance can be slower on Linux systems</li>
<li>Requires NTFS-3G drivers on Linux</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="exfat-the-modern-cross-platform-solution">exFAT: The Modern Cross-Platform Solution</h3>
<pre><code class="language-bash"># Install exFAT tools
sudo apt install exfatprogs    # Ubuntu/Debian
sudo dnf install exfatprogs    # Fedora/RHEL

# Format the card
sudo mkfs.exfat /dev/sdX
</code></pre>
<p><strong>Pros:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Designed specifically for flash media</li>
<li>Excellent cross-platform compatibility</li>
<li>Handles large files and volumes efficiently</li>
<li>Better than FAT32 for many small files</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Cons:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Less robust than ext4 (no journaling)</li>
<li>Requires additional packages on some Linux distributions</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="fat32-the-legacy-option-not-recommended-for-backups">FAT32: The Legacy Option (Not Recommended for Backups)</h3>
<pre><code class="language-bash">sudo mkfs.vfat -F 32 -s 8 -S 4096 /dev/sdX
</code></pre>
<p><strong>Pros:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Universal compatibility</li>
<li>Simple structure</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Cons:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>4GB file size limitation</li>
<li>Poor handling of many small files</li>
<li>Prone to corruption with large volumes</li>
<li>Not recommended for backup purposes on cards larger than 32GB</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="creating-backups-with-rsync">Creating Backups with rsync</h2>
<p>The <code>rsync</code> utility is the Swiss Army knife of Linux backups. Here's how to leverage it effectively for SD card backups:</p>
<h3 id="basic-backup-command">Basic Backup Command</h3>
<pre><code class="language-bash">rsync -av --progress /source/directory/ /path/to/sdcard/
</code></pre>
<p>The trailing slashes are important! They tell rsync to copy the contents of the source directory rather than the directory itself.</p>
<h3 id="enhanced-integrity-checking">Enhanced Integrity Checking</h3>
<pre><code class="language-bash">rsync -av --progress --checksum /source/directory/ /path/to/sdcard/
</code></pre>
<p>The <code>--checksum</code> option verifies file integrity by comparing file contents rather than just timestamps and sizes. This is slower but catches corruption issues that might otherwise go unnoticed.</p>
<h3 id="dealing-with-problematic-transfers">Dealing with Problematic Transfers</h3>
<pre><code class="language-bash">rsync -av --progress --inplace --no-whole-file --modify-window=1 /source/directory/ /path/to/sdcard/
</code></pre>
<p>This command is particularly useful for troublesome SD cards:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>--inplace</code> updates files directly rather than creating temporary copies</li>
<li><code>--no-whole-file</code> transfers changed parts of files only</li>
<li><code>--modify-window=1</code> allows for slight timestamp differences</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="automating-your-backups">Automating Your Backups</h2>
<p>Create a simple backup script:</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">#!/bin/bash
# SD card backup script with verification and notification

SOURCE=&quot;/path/to/data&quot;
DEST=&quot;/path/to/mounted/sdcard/backup&quot;
LOG=&quot;/home/user/backup_logs/backup_$(date +%Y%m%d_%H%M%S).log&quot;
mkdir -p &quot;$(dirname &quot;$LOG&quot;)&quot;

# Ensure SD card is accessible
if ! [ -d &quot;$DEST&quot; ]; then
    echo &quot;Error: Backup destination not accessible!&quot; | tee &quot;$LOG&quot;
    exit 1
fi

# Check available space
SOURCE_SIZE=$(du -sb &quot;$SOURCE&quot; | cut -f1)
DEST_AVAIL=$(df -P &quot;$DEST&quot; | awk 'NR==2 {print $4 * 1024}')

if [ &quot;$SOURCE_SIZE&quot; -gt &quot;$DEST_AVAIL&quot; ]; then
    echo &quot;Error: Insufficient space on backup device!&quot; | tee -a &quot;$LOG&quot;
    exit 2
fi

# Perform backup with detailed logging
echo &quot;Backup started at $(date)&quot; | tee -a &quot;$LOG&quot;
rsync -avh --progress --checksum --stats &quot;$SOURCE/&quot; &quot;$DEST/&quot; 2&gt;&amp;1 | tee -a &quot;$LOG&quot;

# Verify successful completion
if [ ${PIPESTATUS[0]} -eq 0 ]; then
    echo &quot;Backup completed successfully at $(date)&quot; | tee -a &quot;$LOG&quot;

    # Optional: Send notification
    # notify-send &quot;Backup Successful&quot; &quot;Data has been backed up to SD card&quot;
else
    echo &quot;Backup failed with error at $(date)&quot; | tee -a &quot;$LOG&quot;

    # Optional: Send notification
    # notify-send -u critical &quot;Backup Failed&quot; &quot;SD card backup encountered errors&quot;
fi
</code></pre>
<p>Make it executable with <code>chmod +x backup_script.sh</code> and schedule with cron if needed.</p>
<h2 id="troubleshooting-common-issues">Troubleshooting Common Issues</h2>
<h3 id="filesystem-errors-during-backup">Filesystem Errors During Backup</h3>
<p><strong>Symptoms:</strong> rsync crashes, input/output errors, sudden disconnections
<strong>Common Causes:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>FAT32 limitations with many files or large volumes</li>
<li>Counterfeit card exceeding actual capacity</li>
<li>Card controller issues</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Solutions:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Use ext4 or exFAT filesystem instead of FAT32</li>
<li>Verify card authenticity with F3</li>
<li>Try a different card reader</li>
<li>Break backups into smaller batches</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="slow-transfer-speeds">Slow Transfer Speeds</h3>
<p><strong>Symptoms:</strong> Backup takes excessively long time
<strong>Common Causes:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Low-quality card with poor write performance</li>
<li>Suboptimal card reader</li>
<li>USB bus limitations</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Solutions:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Use a card with higher speed rating (V30+)</li>
<li>Use a dedicated USB 3.0+ card reader</li>
<li>Ensure card reader is connected directly to computer, not through a hub</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="data-corruption-after-backup">Data Corruption After Backup</h3>
<p><strong>Symptoms:</strong> Files unreadable or truncated after backup completes
<strong>Common Causes:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Improper ejection/unmounting</li>
<li>Power fluctuations during write operations</li>
<li>Filesystem not suitable for the card</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Solutions:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Always properly unmount before removing: <code>sudo umount /path/to/sdcard</code></li>
<li>Use a powered card reader</li>
<li>Consider using a journaling filesystem like ext4</li>
<li>Use the <code>--checksum</code> option with rsync to verify integrity</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="best-practices-for-sd-card-backups">Best Practices for SD Card Backups</h2>
<ol>
<li><strong>Always verify your backups.</strong> Don't assume the data was written correctly.</li>
<li><strong>Label your cards.</strong> Physical labels with date and content information prevent confusion.</li>
<li><strong>Store cards properly.</strong> Use protective cases and keep away from magnetic fields.</li>
<li><strong>Rotate multiple cards.</strong> Don't rely on a single backup medium.</li>
<li><strong>Periodically refresh data.</strong> SD cards can lose data over very long storage periods (years).</li>
<li><strong>Check filesystem integrity regularly:</strong> <code>fsck /dev/sdX</code></li>
</ol>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>SD cards can be excellent backup solutions for Linux users when properly configured and managed. By choosing the right card, verifying its authenticity, selecting an appropriate filesystem, and using robust backup commands, you can create a reliable, portable backup solution.</p>
<p>Remember that while SD cards offer convenience, they should be part of a broader backup strategy. Consider the 3-2-1 backup rule: three copies of your data, on two different media types, with one copy stored off-site.</p>
<hr />
<p><strong>Credits:</strong> Meta image <a href="https://pixabay.com/photos/memory-memory-card-electronics-3879753/">Memory Card Electronics</a> by <a href="https://kieutruong.com/">kieutruongphoto</a></p>
<hr>
<p>Thank you for reading!</p>
<p>This article was written by Ramiro Gómez using open source software and the assistance of AI tools. While I strive to ensure accurate information, please verify any details independently before taking action. For more articles, visit the <a href="https://geeksta.net/geeklog/">Geeklog on geeksta.net</a>.</p>        ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title><![CDATA[Wiki Story: Turn Wikipedia Articles into Captivating Narratives]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[https://geeksta.net/geeklog/wiki-story-introduction/]]></link>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>Transform Wikipedia articles into captivating short stories with Wiki Story. Adjust storytelling styles, from factual to imaginative, and make learning enjoyable!</p><img src="/img/tools/wiki-story.png" alt="Preview Image">]]></description>
        <guid><![CDATA[https://geeksta.net/geeklog/wiki-story-introduction/]]></guid>
        <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2025 13:25:04 </pubDate>
        <content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <p>Have you ever wished history, science, or art could be told like a gripping tale? Meet <a href="https://agent.ai/agent/wiki-story?referrer=yaph">Wiki Story</a>, the AI agent that transforms Wikipedia articles into engaging short stories. Whether you're craving a concise, factual narrative or a imaginative twist, Wiki Story delivers, blending knowledge with creativity.</p>
<h2 id="how-it-works">How It Works:</h2>
<p><img alt="Wiki Story" src="/img/tools/wiki-story.png" /></p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Pick a Wikipedia Article</strong> – Enter the title of any English Wikipedia article that sparks your curiosity.</li>
<li><strong>Adjust the Creativity Level</strong> – Set the tone of your story on a scale from 1 to 10. A level of 1 delivers a clear and factual narrative, while a level of 10 adds a playful and imaginative touch.</li>
<li><strong>Read Your Story</strong> – Let Wiki Story craft a unique narrative that blends accurate information with your preferred level of creativity.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="why-choose-wiki-story">Why Choose Wiki Story?</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Learn Differently:</strong> Complex topics become accessible, fun, and easy to remember.</li>
<li><strong>Inspire Curiosity:</strong> Transform dull facts into exciting adventures.</li>
<li><strong>Personalized for You:</strong> Control how creative or factual the story gets.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="from-classroom-to-campfire">From Classroom to Campfire</h2>
<p>Whether you're a student looking to turn history into an easy-to-digest tale, a teacher seeking to captivate your classroom, or just a curious mind wanting to explore the world in a new way—Wiki Story makes learning an adventure.</p>
<h2 id="try-wiki-story-today">Try Wiki Story Today</h2>
<p>Begin your storytelling adventure today! Transform knowledge into engaging, inspiring, and whimsical stories. Visit the <a href="https://agent.ai/agent/wiki-story?referrer=yaph">Wiki Story agent page</a> to get started.</p>
<hr>
<p>Thank you for reading!</p>
<p>This article was written by Ramiro Gómez using open source software and the assistance of AI tools. While I strive to ensure accurate information, please verify any details independently before taking action. For more articles, visit the <a href="https://geeksta.net/geeklog/">Geeklog on geeksta.net</a>.</p>        ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
</channel></rss>